Richard Henry Lee Papers 1763-1823 Mss.B.L51
American Philosophical Society
Richard Henry Lee Papers
1763-1823
Mss.B.L51
American Philosophical Society
0.5 Linear feet
A politician and arch revolutionary, Richard Henry Lee was an impassioned supporter of American independence from the mid-1760s. Born into one of the most prominent families in the colony on January 20, 1732, Lee was bred to a political life, serving in the Virginia House of Burgesses during the Stamp Act and Non-importation crises, helping convey his state into the revolutionary camp. As a delegate to the Continental Congress, Lee was the first to officially move that a declaration of independence be drafted, and he ended his public career as a principled opponent of ratification of the Constitution and as Virginia's first U.S. Senator. He died at home in Virginia in June 1794. A small, but highly valuable collection, the papers of Richard Henry Lee document the political life and activities of one of the most ardent revolutionaries in Virginia. The 0.5 linear feet of letters (193 items), most addressed to Lee, are an important resource for study of pre-Revolutionary political agitation in Virginia, the increasing connections forged between the colonies, and the political course of the war. To a lesser degree the collection documents Lee's late-life anti-federalism. Among the major correspondents are Lee's brothers Arthur and William, and such leaders in the revolutionary cause as George Washington, Samuel Adams, Charles Lee, John Adams, and Thomas Paine.
Lee, Richard Henry, 1732-1794
Bibliography
Most of the correspondence in the collection is reproduced in:
Lee, Richard Henry, Memoir of the Life of Richard Henry Lee (Philadelphia: Carey and Lee, 1825) Call no.: B L51l.
Ballagh, James Curtis, ed., The Letters of Richard Henry Lee, 2 vols. (New York: MacMillan, 1911-1914) Call no.: B L51b.
Hays, Isaac Minis, "A Note on the History of the Jefferson Manuscript Draught of the Declaration of Independence in the Library of the American Philosophical Society," Transactions of the American Philosophical Society 37 (1898): 88-107.
Early American History Note
This collection of Richard Henry Lee correspondence is most notable for its rich content relating to the movement for Independence, military matters during the war, and the politics of ratification and the early republic. Because much of the correspondence is incoming, the letters offer insight into a wide range of other topics – and snapshots of events happening in areas beyond Lee’s home state of Virginia. Frequent correspondents during the revolutionary era include John Dickinson, Samuel Adams, Benjamin Rush, and George Washington, among others. Almost all of these letters contain discussions of politics that offer significant insight into the letter writer’s political thought and rich details on events happening throughout British America. Among Rush’s correspondence is a series of letters written following the Battle of Princeton that relate the treatment Rush administered to a Hugh Mercer, who later died of his wounds.
Other Finding Aids note
Calendar of the Correspondence Relating to the American Revolution of Brigadier-General George Weedon, Hon. Richard Henry Lee, Hon. Arthur Lee, and Major-General Nathanael Greene, in the Library of the American Philosophical Society (Philadelphia: American Philosophical Society, 1900) Call no.: 973.3 Am4.
Separated Materials note
The Lee Papers originally included a manuscript penultimate draft of Thomas Jefferson's Declaration of Independence written on about July 1, 1776. The draft is housed separately.
Related Archival Materials note
The Lee Papers are one of several important collections at the APS for documenting the American Revolution, including the papers of Benjamin Franklin (B F85), Nathanael Greene (B G83), and George Weedon (B W41). The Library also has eight reels of microfilm of the Lee Family Papers at the University of Virginia (Film 1240).
The correspondence of Richard Henry Lee and his family is widely scattered, with individual letters and small groups located at a large number of repositories. The major collections are:
Richard Henry Lee Papers, 1742-1795. Alderman Library, University of Virginia (8 microfilm reels).
Lee Family Papers, 1722-1892. Huntington Library (100 items)
Richard Henry Lee Papers, 1785-1796. Alderman Library, University of Virginia (50 items). Chiefly concerning the settlement of Lee's estate.
Richard Henry Lee Papers and Lee Family Papers. Virginia Historical Society.
Richard Henry Lee Papers and Lee Family Papers. Library of Congress.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of Richard Henry Lee, Jr., June 12, 1825.
Scope and Contents note
A small, but highly valuable collection, the papers of Richard Henry Lee document the political life and activities of one of the most ardent revolutionaries in Virginia. The 0.5 linear feet of letters (193 items), most addressed to Lee, are an important resource for study of pre-Revolutionary political agitation in Virginia, the increasing connections forged between the colonies, and the political course of the war. To a lesser degree the collection documents Lee's late-life anti-federalism. Among the major correspondents are Lee's brothers Arthur and William, and such leaders in the revolutionary cause as George Washington, Samuel Adams, Charles Lee, John Adams, and Thomas Paine.
After Lexington and Concord, the letters from Charles Lee sometimes seem overwrought with emotion and excitement, as when he wrote: by the eternal God if you do not declare immediately for positive independence We are all ruin'd -- there is a poorness of spirit and languor in the late proceedings of the Congress that I confess frightens me so much, that at times I regret having embark'd my all, my fortune, life and reputation..." (May 10, 1776).
Several of the 25 letters written by George Washington provide exceptionally important information on the prosecution of the war, the testy relationship between Washington and a demanding Congress, and other topics. In a letter written July 10, 1775, Washington provides his assessment of the siege of Boston; his letter of Dec. 26, 1775, discusses Lord Dunmore's "diabolical" proclamation to arm slaves; the letter of June 12, 1784, requests quiet assistance for the impoverished Thomas Paine.
Lee's other major correspondents include the Boston radical Samuel Adams (15 letters), Charles Lee (6 letters), and Gen. Adam Stephen (5 letters), but the selection includes important letters from a number of eminent men associated with the revolutionary struggle, including John Adams, Baron de Kalb, Horatio Gates, Conte de Grasse, Patrick Henry, John Jay, Thomas Jefferson, the Marquis de Lafayette, Henry Laurens, Thomas Paine, Kasimerz Pulaski, Benjamin Rush, George Weedon, and George Wythe.
Biographical/Historical note
Tall and aristocratic in bearing, Richard Henry Lee was an impassioned supporter of American independence in Virginia and later a prominent antagonist of the federal constitution. Born into one of the most prominent families in the colony on January 20, 1732, Lee was bred to a political life. The son of Thomas Lee, one-time president of the governing Council of Virginia and a founder of the Ohio Company, and Hannah Ludwell of "Stratford Hall," Westmorland County, Lee benefited from a superior education, attending the Wakefield Academy in England for seven years before returning in 1751 to enter the family calling, public service. Four of his brothers were active in Revolutionary and post-revolutionary politics: Francis Lightfoot Lee joined Richard as a signer of the Declaration of Independence, Thomas Ludwell Lee helped write Virginia's resolve for independence and was later chosen to the state supreme court, and Arthur and William Lee became noted diplomats.
Appointed justice of the peace for Westmoreland County in 1757, Lee was first elected to the House of Burgesses in the next year, aged 25. From the first, he pitted himself in the radical wing of Virginia politics. His first speech as a legislator was a proposal to ban the importation of slaves into Virginia, and he earned a reputation as a zealous -- occasionally overly zealous -- political combatant for the part he played in a dispute with the Speaker, John Robinson, over a rivalry between the Ohio Land Company and Robinson's Loyal Land Company. However it was only with the political disputes between the colonies and England after the end of the Seven Years War that Lee's characteristically incendiary style began to emerge.
Although Lee had initially applied to become a collector under the Stamp Act of 1765, he very soon turned to the opposition, becoming a leader of the most vocal and extreme wing. With his brothers Thomas and Francis Lightfoot, Lee gathered 115 signatures to the "Westmoreland Resolves," a petition that threatened "danger and disgrace" to anyone who paid the tax. An act of overt sedition, and one of the earliest to threaten physical violence, the Resolves were a key turning point in the pre-revolutionary struggle.
After recovering from a hunting accident that cost him several fingers on one hand in 1768, Lee returned to a position of prominence in the nascent independence movement, helping to galvanize support for the Non-importation agreements. From England, his brother Arthur kept him informed of English news and political gossip and of the shifting currents toward the colonial crisis. But the specifics of Lee's part in the resistance in Virginia were ultimately less important than his efforts to strengthen political unity between the colonies and to foster a systematic intercolonial exchange of information. In the process, he forged a close working relationship with the Massachusetts firebrand Samuel Adams, and the two remained close throughout the ensuing decades of political strife.
From his seat in the Continental Congress, Lee emerged as an orator of unusual skill and power, urging the colonies to stay the oppositional course and, in July 1775, becoming one of the first to recommend forming independent state governments. Perhaps his signal claim to public renown came on May 17, 1776, when he submitted a resolution to Congress stating that the colonies should declare "That these united Colonies are, and ought to be, fee and independent States, that they are absolved from all allegiance from the British crown, and than all political connection between America and State of Great Britain is, and ought to be, totally dissolved." Before the debate over the declaration of independence took place, however, Lee had returned to Virginia to assist his home state establish its new government.
In later years, Lee supported the Ordinance of 1785 and the Northwest Ordinance, believing (as a child of the Ohio Company) that revenue from western lands would be beneficial to the new state, and he unsuccessfully submitted an amendment to allow federal support for religion. Increasingly poor health prevented him from taking up his position as delegate to either the federal constitutional convention of 1787 or the state ratification convention in 1788, however Lee contributed to the debate as author of the seminal Anti-federalist tract Letters from the Federal Farmer to the Republican (1787-1788). Supportive of much of the federal apparatus (centralization of foreign affairs, commerce, money, and post), he nevertheless rejected the constitution for what he saw as anti-democratic tendencies in a powerful executive, the lack of a bill of rights, and the too limited number of seats in the House of Representatives.
Following the ratification, however, Lee grudgingly came around to support the federal government and was appointed as one of the state's first two Senators in 1789, both Anti-federalists. Once again he took up the cause of an amendment to allow public support for religion, but his term in office was interrupted repeatedly by ill health and by the effects of a carriage accident. Finally, half way through his term on October 8, 1792, he was forced to resign and retire from public life.
Lee was twice married, first to Anne Aylett in 1757, with whom he had four children, and second, in 1768, to Anne Gaskins Pinckard, with whom he had five children. After leaving the Senate, Lee returned to his estate, "Chantilly," where he died on June 19, 1794.
Adams, John, 1735-1826; Adams, Samuel, 1722-1803; Barré, Isaac, 1726-1802; Carmichael, William, d. 1795; Chase, Samuel, 1741-1811; Conway, Thomas, 1733-ca.1800; De Kalb, Johann, 1721-1780; Dickinson, John, 1732-1808; Gates, Horatio, 1728-1806; Grasse, Francois Joseph Paul de Grasse, comte de, 1722-1788; Henry, Patrick, 1726-1799; Holker, John, 1719-1786; Jay, John, 1745- 1829; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826; Jennings, Edmund; Johnson, Thomas, 1732-1819; Jones, William; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834; Laurens, Henry, 1724-1792; Lee, Arthur, 1740-1792; Lee, John; Lee, William, 1739-1795; Lovell, James, 1737-1814; Martin, John; McKean, Thomas, 1734-1817; Mifflin, Thomas, 1744-1800; Monroe, James, 1758-1831; Morris, Gouverneur, 1752-1816; Page, John, 1744-1808; Page, Mann; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809; Pendleton, Edmund, 1721-1803; Pulaski, Kazimierz, 1747-1779; Reed, Joseph, 1741-1785; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; Schuyler, Philip John, 1733-1804; Shippen, William, 1736?-1808; Stephen, Adam; Sullivan, James, 1744-1808; Washington, George, 1732-1799; Weedon, George,1734-1793.; Whipple, William, 1730-1785; Wythe, George, 1726-1806; American Revolution; Early National Politics; Great Britain--Politics and government--18th century; Military History; Non-importation agreements, 1768-1769; Political Correspondence; Stamp Act, 1765; United States--History--Revolution, 1775-1783; United States--History--Revolution, 1775-1783--Causes; United States--Politics and government--1783-1789; United States--Politics and government--To 1775; Virginia--Politics and government--Revolution, 1775-1783
- Richard Henry Lee Papers, 1763-1823; 0.5 lin. feet (Box 1)
  - ALS Cy to John Dickinson, 1763 April 4; 2p.; Lee, Richard Henry, 1732-1794
  - ALS to Arthur Lee, 1766 February 22; 1p.; Adanson, Dr.
    Scope and Contents note
    In Latin
  - ALS to [George Wythe], 1766 July 25; 3p.; Lee, Richard Henry, 1732-1794
    Vindication against being friendly to the Stamp Act
  - ALS to Arthur Lee, 1767 October 31; 2p.; Cardross, Lord
  - ALS to D. DeBirdt, 1768 May 14; 4p.; Adams, Samuel
    Massachusetts politics; Stamp Act; Non-Importation agreement
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1768 December 27; 4p.; Lee, Arthur, 1740-1792
  - ALS Cy to John Dickinson, 1768 August 10; 6p.; Lee, Richard Henry, 1732-1794
    Includes copies of Lee to Dickinson, 1768 Nov. 26, and Dickinson to Lee, 1768 August 10, 1769 January 16, and 1773 May 30
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1768 December 27; 4p.; Lee, Arthur, 1740-1792
    Melancholy state of politics in England. Shelburne is sound, but not likely to lead. Farmer's letters widely read, but to little purpose.
  - ALS Cy to Richard Henry Lee, 1769 June 22; 2p.; Dickinson, John
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1769 August 15; 6p.; Lee, Arthur, 1740-1792
    Complex state of British politics.
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1769 September 18; 2p.; Lee, Arthur, 1740-1792
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1769 September or October; 3p.; Lee, Arthur, 1740-1792
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1769 November 15; 4p.; Lee, Arthur, 1740-1792
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1769 November 19; 2p.; Lee, Arthur, 1740-1792
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1769 December 3; 3p.; Lee, Arthur, 1740-1792
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1770 May 20; 2p.; Lee, Arthur, 1740-1792
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1770 October 20; 2p.; Lee, Arthur, 1740-1792
  - ALS to Arthur Lee, 1771 January 31; 2p.; Barré, Isaac, 1726-1802
    "I see you lament, with all the feelings of true Patriotism, that the Firmness of America has at last given way to thte combined arts of ministerial and mercantile wickedness..."
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1771 August 17; 3p.; Jennings, Edmund
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1771 December 29; 2p.; Jennings, Edmund
    Plus 2p. inclosure
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1772 Aug. 17; 3p.; Lee, Arthur, 1740-1792
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1773 April 10; 4p.; Adams, Samuel
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1774 March 18; 4p.; Lee, Arthur, 1740-1792
    Urges unity in opposition to British attempts to split Massachusetts from the other colonies.
  - Petition to Great Britain. Parliament, 1774 March 26; 3p.; "Several Natives of America"
    Remonstrance against financial reprisals taken against Boston tea party.
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1774 July 15; 3p.; Adams, Samuel
    Bostonians repond to the Port Bill by resolving to withstand the hardships.
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1774 August 9; 1p.; Washington, George
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1774 Aug. 27; 3p.; Stephen, Adam
    "The Fate of America depends upon your Meeting and the Eyes of the European World hang upon you waiting the Event." Need for arms in Virginia: "At the Congress this ought to be privately taken into consideration -- A plan laid for encouraging Numbers of Gun lock smiths to come in -- A number of Locks to be imported with Caution -- to prevent suspicion and as many arms as could be got -- I imagine that we want 100,000 stand of Arms. We have great difficulty in fitting out the few men we want on this occasion."
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1774 Dec. 22; 3p.; Lee, Arthur, 1740-1792
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1775 Feb. 1; 4p.; Stephen, Adam
  - ADS, ca.1775 Feb. 2; 3p.; Lee, Richard Henry, 1732-1794
    Opinion re: Committee of King George's County, Va.
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1775 Feb. 17; 2p.; Stephen, Adam
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1775 March 21; 4p.; Adams, Samuel
    Gage and British troops more insolent than ever. Oration to commemorate the Boston Massacre.
  - Petition (ADf fragment) to George III, 1775 April 5; 1p.; United States. Continental Congress.
  - ADf to London (England). Lord Mayor, 1775 May; 1p.; United States. Continental Congress.
  - ADfS to Gouverneur Morris, 1775 May 28; 4p.; Lee, Richard Henry, 1732-1794
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1775 June 1; 3p.; Philopatria
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1775 July 10; 4p.; Washington, George
    Situation of the army besieging Boston: "between you and me I think we are in an exceeding dangerous situation, as our numbers are not much larger than we suppose, from the best accts. we are able to get, those of the Enemy to be."
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1775 Sept. 2; 2p.; Lee, Charles
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1775 Sept. 23; 2p.; Stephen, Adam
    Wiandots and other Indians between Detroit and Niagara are "greatly divided."
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1775 Oct. 19; 1p.; Schuyler, Philip John, 1733-1804
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1775 Oct. 29; 2p.; Washington, George
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1775 Nov. 27; 4p.; Washington, George
    State of the army and ships available. "For Godsake hurry the signers of money that our want may be supplied."
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1775 Dec. 12; 4p.; Lee, Charles
    Proposes seizing the estates of all opponents of liberty and banishing them to internal exile; fortify and garrison New York or destroy it.
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1775 Dec. 26; 4p.; Washington, George
    Response to Dunmore's "diabolical" proclamation to arm slaves.
  - ALS Cy to Lord Piercy, 1775; 2p.; Lee, Charles
  - Petition Cy to George III, 1775; 2p.; London (England). Lord Mayor and Common Council.
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1775; 2p.; Morris, Gouverneur, 1752-1816
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1776 Feb. 20; 3p.; Page, John, 1744-1808
  - ALS to Charles Lee, 1776 Feb.; 1p.; Lee, Richard Henry, 1732-1794
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1776 Apr. 4; 3p.; Washington, George
    Lakes are impassable and troops cannot be spared. Flight of British from Boston. Need a hospital badly for the troops.
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1776 Apr. 5; 4p.; Lee, Charles
    Complaints of timidity of political leadership. Bland says the author of Common Sense is a blockhead.
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1776 Apr. 8; 1p.; Pendleton, Edmund, 1721-1803
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1776 Apr. 12; 4p.; Lee, Charles
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1776 May 10; 3p.; Lee, Charles
    "by the eternal God if you do not declare immediately for positive independence We are all ruin'd -- there is a poorness of spirit and languor in the late proceedings of the Congress that I confess frightens me so much, that at times I regret having embark'd my all, my fortune, life and reputation..."
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1776 May 18; 1p.; Washington, George
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1776 July 15; 3p.; Adams, Samuel
    Howe in New York. "Our Declaration of Independency has given Vigor to the Spirits of the People. Had this decisive measure been taken Nine Months ago, it is my opinion that Canada would at this time have been in our hands..."
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1776 July 30; 3p.; Chase, Samuel, 1741-1811
  - ADf Proposed additions to the instructions given to the Commissioners going to France, 1776 Oct.; 2p.; United States. Continental Congress.
    Authorization to seek arms and troops from France and Spain.
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1776 Dec. 17; 2p.; Shippen, William, 1736?-1808
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1776 Dec. 20; 4p.; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813
    "We are much blamed by the Whigs and ridiculed by the Tories for leaving Philada. so suddenly."
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1776 Dec. 20; 4p.; Shippen, William, 1736?-1808
    Recommendations to Congress on the needs of military hospitals.
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1776 Dec. 20; 4p.; Shippen, William, 1736?-1808
  - ALS to Commissioners to France, 1776 Dec. 21; 2p.; United States. Continental Congress.
    News of progress of war.
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1776 Dec. 21; 4p.; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813
  - Cy to the States, 1776 Dec. 29; 1p.; United States. Continental Congress.
    Appointing Lee, Adams, and Wilson as a committee to draft a letter explaining why Congress has expanded the powers given to Washington
  - ALS to Commissioners to France, 1776 Dec. 30; 4p.; United States. Continental Congress.
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1776 Dec. 30; 4p.; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813
    "There is no soil so dear to a soldier as that which is marked with the footsteps of a flying enemy."
  - Subscription in support of John Sears, 1776; 1p.; Davenport, James
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1776 [i.e. 1777] Jan. 6; 3p.; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813
    News of Battle of Princeton.
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1777 Jan. 7; 4p.; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813
    Mercer is improving after wounding at Princeton. More news of Princeton.
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1777 Jan. 10; 1p.; Washington, George
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1777 Jan. 14; 4p.; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813
    Suggests commissary send supplies to American POWs. Rumors that the British have raised large numbers of Russians and Germans to serve in America; news of Battle of Trenton reaches New York.
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1777 Jan. 14; 3p.; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1777 Jan. 17; 3p.; Shippen, William, 1736?-1808
  - ALS to Commissioners to France, 1777 Feb. 19; 2p.; United States. Continental Congress.
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1777 Mar. 6; 2p.; Washington, George
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1777 Mar. 17; 1p.; Carmichael, William, d. 1795
    Arthur Lee is in Spain. Introducing the Marquis de Lafayette and Baron deKalb.
  - ALS Cy to George Washington, 1777 Apr. 10; 1p.; United States. Congress
  - ALS to Richard Henry Lee, 1777 Apr. 22; 2p.; Stephen, Adam
    Jerseymen and Virginians will bear the burden of fighting while "The Myriads of the North -- the Great Women... seem Cloy'd of fighting and are wonderfully backward in turning out."